{"author": "Robert R. Harr","data": [{"chapter": "3.4","questions": [{"data": [{"choices": ["Increase of tolerance to self-antigens","Loss of tolerance to self-antigens","Increase in clonal deletion of mutant cells","Manifestation of immunosuppression"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Loss of tolerance to self-antigens","explanation": "Autoimmunity is a loss of tolerance to self-antigens and the subsequent formation of autoantibodies"},"question": "What is a general definition for autoimmunity?","reference": "Immunology/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Autoimmunity/Definitions/1"},{"choices": ["Anti-DNA assay","Extractable nuclear antigen (ENA) testing","Retest ANA in 3 to 6 months","CH50 complement assay"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Retest ANA in 3 to 6 months","explanation": "Approximately 25% of women in this age range may have low titer–positive ANA assays with no demonstrable connective tissue disease. A patient with anti-DNA–positive SLE would be expected to have a much higher titer (greater than 160) in an IFA. A similar titer would be expected for an ENA positive specimen, although the pattern would be speckled. Complement testing would not be indicated with this low titer in a 55-year-old female"},"question": "An ANA test is performed on a specimen from a 55-year-old woman who has unexplained joint pain. The IFA result shows a titer of 40 and a homogeneous pattern. The appropriate follow-up for this patient is:","reference": "Immunology/Correlate laboratory data with physiological processes/IF/2"},{"choices": ["Mixed connective tissue disease (MCTD)","RA","SLE","Scleroderma"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "SLE","explanation": "The rim or peripheral pattern seen in indirect immunofluorescence techniques is most commonly found in cases of active SLE. The responsible autoantibody is highly correlated to anti–double-stranded DNA (anti-dsDNA)"},"question": "Which disease is likely to show a rim (peripheral) pattern in an immunofluorescence (IF) microscopy test for ANA?","reference": "Immunology/Correlate laboratory data with physiological processes/IF/2"},{"choices": ["IFA on human epithelial type 2 (HEp-2) cells","Specific ENA ELISA tests","Specific anti-DNA ELISA","Rheumatoid factor (RF) assay"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Rheumatoid factor (RF) assay","explanation": "The ANA ELISA is a screening assay. A positive result may be followed up by more specific antibody ELISA tests or an ANA IFA to determine pattern and titer. The ANA ELISA does not screen for RF"},"question": "A patient’s specimen is strongly positive in an ANA ELISA. Which of the following would not be an appropriate follow-up to this result?","reference": "Immunology/Select tests/ANA Confirmation/2"},{"choices": ["Antihistone antibodies","Anticentromere antibodies","Anti-ENA (anti-Smith [anti-Sm] and anti-ribonucleoprotein [anti-RNP]) antibodies","Anti-RNA antibodies"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Antihistone antibodies","explanation": "Antihistone antibodies (and also anti-DNA antibodies) cause the solid or homogeneous pattern, which is commonly found in patients with SLE, RA, MCTD, and Sjögren syndrome. Antibodies to the centromere of chromosomes is a marker for the CREST (calcinosis, Raynaud phenomenon, esophageal dysfunction, sclerodactyly, and telangiectasia) form of systemic sclerosis"},"question": "What type of antibodies is represented by the homogeneous pattern in the IFA for ANAs?","reference": "Immunology/Correlate laboratory data with physiological processes/IF/1"},{"choices": ["MCTD", "RA", "SLE", "Scleroderma"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "SLE","explanation": "High titer anti-Sm is indicative of SLE. Anti-Sm is an antibody against saline ENAs. and causes a speckled pattern of immunofluorescence"},"question": "What disease is indicated by a high titer of anti-Sm antibody?","reference": "Immunology/Correlate laboratory data with physiological processes/IF/2"},{"choices": ["MCTD", "Sjögren syndrome", "SLE", "Scleroderma"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "MCTD","explanation": "All of the diseases except MCTD may cause a nucleolar pattern of immunofluorescence. Nucleolar fluorescence is caused by anti-RNA antibodies and is seen in about 50% of patients with scleroderma"},"question": "Which disease is least likely when a nucleolar pattern occurs in an IFA for ANAs?","reference": "Immunology/Correlate laboratory data with physiological processes/IF/2"},{"choices": ["Antihistone antibodies","Anti-dsDNA antibodies","Anti-ENA (anti-Sm and anti-RNP) antibodies","Anti-RNA antibodies"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Anti-RNA antibodies","explanation": "Anti-RNA antibodies are represented by the nucleolar pattern. This pattern may be seen in most systemic autoimmune diseases and is especially common in patients with scleroderma. Anti-RNA and anti-Sm are not usually found in patients with MCTD. This is a syndrome involving aspects of SLE, RA, scleroderma, and polymyositis. The immunofluorescence pattern most often seen in MCTD is the speckled pattern caused by anti-RNP"},"question": "What antibodies are represented by the nucleolar pattern in the IFA for ANAs?","reference": "Immunology/Correlate laboratory data with physiological processes/IF/1"},{"choices": ["Multiplex or ELISA test for anti-Sm and anti-RNP","IFA using Crithidia as substrate","Slide agglutination testing","Laboratory tests cannot distinguish between these disorders"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Multiplex or ELISA test for anti-Sm and anti-RNP","explanation": "Line blots, multiplex, and ELISA assays, using purified or recombinant antigens, are available for differentiating anti-RNP from anti-Sm. Anti-Sm with or without anti-RNP is found in approximately one third of patients with SLE. Anti-RNP in the absence of anti-Sm is found in over 95% of patients with MCTD"},"question": "Which test would best distinguish between SLE and MCTD?","reference": "Immunology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize and report the need for additional testing/Autoimmune/Testing/3"},{"choices": ["Antifibrillarin antibody","Anti–ribosomal P antibody","A serum with nucleolar and homogeneous patterns","Technical artifact"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Antifibrillarin antibody","explanation": "Antifibrillarin antibody has this appearance. Ribosomal P antibody has nucleolar staining and a background homogeneous and cytoplasmic stain. A combination nucleolar/homogeneous specimen will also show homogeneous staining in the interphase cells. This pattern is not seen in typical technical artifacts"},"question": "An ANA test on HEp-2 cells shows nucleolar staining in interphase cells and dense chromatin staining in mitotic cells. The most likely cause of this staining pattern is:","reference": "Immunology/Correlate laboratory data with physiological processes/IF/1"},{"choices": ["Homogeneous or solid","Peripheral or rim","Speckled","Nucleolar"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Speckled","explanation": "A speckled pattern is often caused by the presence of antibodies against the ENAs, such as Sm, RNP, SSA, and SSB. Homogeneous and rim patterns suggest antibodies to dsDNA. The homogeneous pattern may also be seen with antibodies to deoxyribonuclear protein, which is not an ENA. Nucleolar patterns often indicate antibodies to RNA or fibrillarin"},"question": "Which immunofluorescence pattern indicates the need for ENA testing by multiplex, line blots, or ELISA assays?","reference": "Immunology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize and report the need for additional testing/Autoimmune/Testing/3"},{"choices": ["Whole IgM molecules","Fc portion of the IgG molecule","Fab portion of the IgG molecule","Fc portion of the IgM molecule"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Fc portion of the IgG molecule","explanation": "RFs react with the Fc portion of the IgG molecule and are usually IgM. This is the basis of rapid agglutination tests for RA. Particles of latex or cells are coated with IgG. Addition of serum containing RF results in visible agglutination"},"question": "Which of the following is used in rapid slide tests for detection of RFs?","reference": "Immunology/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/RA/Testing/1"},{"choices": ["Nephelometric measurement of anti-IgG","Agglutination testing for RF","Anti-CCP","IFA for ANAs"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "IFA for ANAs","explanation": "Patients with RA often show a homogeneous pattern of fluorescence in tests for ANAs. However, this pattern is seen in a wide range of systemic autoimmune diseases and in many normal persons at a titer below 10. The first two methods listed may be used to identify anti-IgG, which is one laboratory criterion used to establish a diagnosis of RA. Anti-CCP is an additional laboratory criterion used in the RA diagnostic algorithm"},"question": "Which of the following methods is least likely to give a definitive result for the diagnosis of RA?","reference": "Immunology/Select routine laboratory procedures/Autoimmune/RA/Testing/1"},{"choices": ["Atrophic gastritis","Autoimmune hepatitis","Myasthenia gravis","Sjögren syndrome"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Autoimmune hepatitis","explanation": "Antibodies to smooth muscle are found in the serum of up to 70% of patients with active chronic hepatitis and up to 50% of patients with primary biliary cirrhosis"},"question": "Which disease might be indicated by antibodies to smooth muscle?","reference": "Immunology/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Autoimmune/Testing/1"},{"choices": ["Graves disease and Hashimoto thyroiditis","Myasthenia gravis","Granulomatous thyroid disease","Addison disease"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Graves disease and Hashimoto thyroiditis","explanation": "Antibodies to thyroid peroxidase may be detected in both Graves disease (hyperthyroidism) and Hashimoto thyroiditis (hypothyroidism). If a positive result is found to thyroid peroxidase, thyroxine levels and clinical presentation can be used to distinguish between the two diseases"},"question": "Antibodies to thyroid peroxidase may appear in which of the following diseases?","reference": "Immunology/Select routine laboratory procedures/Autoimmune/Testing/1"},{"choices": ["To regulate levels of injected insulin","To diagnose IDDM","To rule out the presence of other autoimmune diseases","To screen susceptible individuals prior to destruction of β-cells"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "To screen susceptible individuals prior to destruction of β-cells","explanation": "Fasting hyperglycemia and hemoglobin A1C levels are the primary findings used to diagnose IDDM. For individuals with an inherited susceptibility to the development of IDDM, laboratory tests for the detection of antibodies to islet cells and insulin may help to initiate early treatment before complete destruction of β-cells"},"question": "What is the main use of laboratory tests to detect antibodies to islet cells and insulin in cases of insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus (IDDM)?","reference": "Immunology/Select routine laboratory procedures/Autoimmune/IDDM/Testing/1"},{"choices": ["IgG level","HLA DQ2 and DQ8 typing","HLA DR3 and DR7 typing","IgM level"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "HLA DQ2 and DQ8 typing","explanation": "Although antibodies to tissue transglutaminase and gliadin are often found in celiac disease, their combined sensitivity is less than 100%. Celiac disease is almost exclusively associated with the presence of HLA DQ2 and/or HLA DQ8. These HLA genes are not diagnostic of celiac disease, but provide a testing alternative in antibody-negative individuals who meet the clinical diagnostic criteria for celiac disease"},"question": "A patient presents with clinical symptoms of celiac disease. Tests for anti-tissue transglutaminase and antigliadin antibodies are negative. Which of the following tests should be ordered?","reference": "Immunology/Select routine laboratory procedures/Autoimmune/Celiac disease/Testing/2"},{"choices": ["Formalin-fixed neutrophils","Unfixed neutrophils","HEp-2 cells","Rabbit kidney tissue"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Formalin-fixed neutrophils","explanation": "Antibodies to neutrophil cytoplasmic antigen demonstrating a perinuclear pattern of fluorescence indicate a diagnosis of vasculitis. However, atypical ANCAs and ANAs also demonstrate a perinuclear staining pattern on ethanol-fixed neutrophils. To differentiate these from pANCA, specimens appearing as pANCAs on ethanol-fixed cells are tested on formalin-fixed neutrophils. The myeloperoxidase-containing granules that coalesce around the nuclear membrane during ethanol fixation will remain in the cytoplasm during formalin fixation. Thus, pANCAs will have a cytoplasmic (cANCA) pattern on a formalin-fixed slide, but ANAs will retain a perinuclear pattern and the fluorescence will be diminished"},"question": "A specimen appears to have a perinuclear staining pattern in an antineutrophil cytoplasmic antibody (ANCA) immunofluorescent assay using ethanol-fixed neutrophils, suggesting the possibility of a perinuclear ANCA (pANCA). On which of the following substrates would this specimen display cytoplasmic speckling?","reference": "Immunology/Select routine laboratory procedures/Autoimmune/ANCA/Testing/2"}],"type": "MULTIPLE_CHOICE"}],"topic": "Autoimmune Diseases"}],"edition": "5th","title": "Medical Laboratory Science Review"}